Does it hurt?
痛むのかい？
I hate how it's come down to this.
悔しいが…こうなっちゃもう、
But I won't be able to fulfil my ambition.
俺の望みが叶うことはねぇ
That money I gathered up
from those samurai...
だが…侍どもから集めたあの金だけは…
I can't just waste it.
無駄にはできねぇ。
It's for the powerless peasants
to take a stand.
あれは…力のねぇ農民たちが立ち上がって生きていくための、
To help them take the step.
大事な元手になるんだ。
I need you to make sure
Dororo understands.
いいか。必ずどろろに連れてやってくれ。
What it is we're fighting for.
俺たちが…何のために戦い続けるのか
Okay.
あぁ
I've hidden the money
past the northern headland in...
金の隠し場所は…北の岬を越えた先
Wait.
待って
You better not tell me.
あたしは聞かないほうがいい。
If you do, I might use it up.
知ったらきっと使っちまう。
Not for any great ambition,
but for Dororo alone.
大願のためじゃなく、どろろ1人のためにね
Engrave it here.
ここに入れておくれ
I won't be able to see it there.
ここなら自分じゃ見えないからね。
I will carry half of your ambition.
あんたの大願、半分はあたしがしょっていく
And the other half...
残りの半分は…
Betrayed this world
And it simmers within
Rupturing my innards
Swelling a reddish black
Until the sun burnt skin ruptures
There is a light
in the depths of the seething darkness
Confirming each other's voices
in the distance
As if to stroke with wet fingertips
I'd like to touch you one day
There is a light
in the depths of the darkness
Confirming each other's voices
in the distance
As if to stroke with wet fingertips
I'd like to touch you one day
#14 The story of Sabame
I see.
なるほどねぇ。
So the map appears
whenever your body is warmed up.
身体があったまると浮かび上がってくるって寸法かい
I'd never taken a warm bath before.
あったけぇ湯に入ったのなんて初めてだったんだ。
I had no idea I had that on my back.
まさかおいらの背中にそんなもんがあったなんて…
I see, I see.
なるほどねぇ。
Your parents have made you bear
quite a heavy burden.
お前さんの親御も、えらいもんを背負わせたもんだ
A little bit before my mama died...
おっかちゃんが死ぬ…ちょっと前にさあ
Listen now, Dororo.
いいかい、どろろ
Remember this well.
よーく覚えておき
This is your papa's lifelong ambition.
これはお父ちゃんの…命がけの願いなんだ。
Carry it on with you.
お前が受け継いで、
And protect it.
守っていくんだよ
She said the other half
would always be close to me.
残りの半分は、おいらのすぐそばにいつもある。
And I'd figure it out when I met someone
I could truly trust.
おいらが心から信じられる相手に出会えたら、その時きっと分かるって…
I see.
なるほど？
I didn't get what she meant, though.
んーまぁ、どういうことかさっぱりわかんなかったし、
I'd more or less forgotten about it.
忘れたつもりでいたけどさ
But good for you.
よかったじゃないか。
You have a wider range of choices now.
これでお前さんたちの道が増えた
Let's say you defeat all the demons
and get his body back.
鬼神どもを斬って身体を取り戻したとして、
What's next?
その後はどうするね？
Money's a grand thing.
金ってのはいいもんだよ？
If you have a full belly,
your heart will be calm and gentle.
腹いっぱい食えれば、心も穏やかになる。
You'll be able to see your surroundings.
周りを見る余裕が生まれて、
And start to think about tomorrow.
明日のことを考え始める
Keeping true to your ambition
when it could mean life or death...
食うや食わずの身の上で、それでも志を貫けるのなんて
that isn't something just anyone can do.
ほんの一握りだけだからねぇ
Even if you defeat a few demons
here and there,
お前さんたちが鬼神の何匹か斬ったところで…
it won't change the world at all.
世の中なんにも変わりゃしないよ
But...
けどね。
what you have on your back
can move people and change the world.
お前さんの背中のそれは、人を動かし世を変える
It's a source of great power.
でかい力の源になる
In other words,
you have a lot more choices now.
ま、要は別のアテができたってことさ。
You could find the money
and live well on it.
金を見つけて遊ぶもよし。
Or use it to build your own domain.
新たな国を築くもよし。
You could even go traveling
to some undiscovered land.
誰も知らない異国へ行くってのも悪かないねぇ
Hey, hold on.
ちょっ、坊さん？
Take some time to think about it.
ここらでちょっくら考えるといいさ
That is, unless...
ま、お前さんがどうしても
you want to destroy Daigo's land
in exchange for your body.
失くした身体と引き換えに醍醐の国を滅ぼしたいってんなら
Just saying.
別だけどね
Hey, bro isn't like that.
なんだよそれ！あにきは別に…
Hey, bro?
なあ…あにき。
What are you going to do
from here on out?
あにきはこの先…どうするの
Kill demons.
鬼神を討つ
I mean, about what the priest said.
そうじゃなくてさ！坊さんも言ってたろ？
After you defeat all the demons
and get your body back.
鬼神をみんな倒して身体全部取り戻したとして、
After all that.
そのあとの話
What do you think I should do...?
ハァ…どうしたらいいと思う？
I just don't know.
おいら…おいら…よくわかんねぇや。
Hey, bro?
なぁ、あにき
Hey, it wouldn't hurt to listen to me
once in a while!
おぉ！？たまにはおいらの話ぐらい
聞いてくれたってバチは当たんねぇだろ！？おい！
Please, buy one...
こうてくだされ
Hey, don't leave me behind like that!
もー！ひでぇよあにき！置いてくなんて。
Please, buy one...
こうてくだされ
I beg you...
お頼み申します
She's gone. What now?
わっ、消えた？なんだよなんだよー！
Bro, what are they?
あにき！こいつら何？
Not demons.
鬼神じゃない
Num-num. Num-num!
マンマ！マンマー！
Carry me.
おんぶ！
Carry me!
Ugh, you're crushing me!
重い！潰れる！うぅ！
Carry me.
おんぶ…おんぶー…
-Help me out, bro!
-Carry me.
助けて、あにき！
Not a demon.
鬼神じゃない
But it's a monster. Help me!
けどバケモンだろ？助けてってば！
Hey, bro!
こらあにきー！
Carry, carry!
おんぶ！おんぶー！
Now you're the one carrying me, jeez!
これじゃおんぶじゃない！吊し上げだ！
Give me a hand, bro.
あにき…代わってくれよー！
Num-num. Num-num!
マンマ…マンマー！
Give me a break,
I'm the one that wants some num-num.
ったく…まんまが食いたいのはおいらの方だってぇの。ハァ…ん？
Hey, it's a temple.
わぁ…あにき、寺だ
It's all burnt inside.
わー…中は黒焦げだ。
But at least we'll be able
to stay dry during the night.
でも夜露ぐらいは凌げるの…かな
What's wrong?
どうしたんだ？
Pee-pee.
おしっこ
Give me a break, I can't take care of you!
じょ…冗談じゃねぇ！そこまで面倒見きれかるっての！
Pee-pee!
おしっこ
No, leave me out of this.
えぇ…やだ！おいら知らない！
Pee-pee!
おしっこ～！
Go pee-pee by yourself!
うわぁ…！自分でしろってそのぐらい！
Pee-pee!
おしっこー！
Stop it! Get off me!
わぁ～！やめろ！おい！離せ！
What's that, bro?
あにき…何だい？それ
I made it go pee outside in the bushes.
あぁ、ちゃんと外の茂みにさせたから。
What?
え、なに…？
Oil?
油？
Why is there oil here?
あ…なんでこんなところに油が？
You mean, somebody burnt this place down?
ここが燃えたのって、またか誰かが火を
Num-num!
マンマァー！
-Num-num.
-You scared me to death, dang it!
マンマー
お前…心の臓が止まるかと思ったぞ！
Now is not the time for this.
今はそれどころじゃないんだってば
Num-num.
マンマー
I don't even know what you eat.
ひぁっ！だいたいお前何食うんだってんだよ。
We're hungry, too.
We don't have any food for monsters...
いらたちも腹ペコなのに、バケモン用のメシなんて！
You don't mean...
あ…まさかお前のメシって
Num-num...
マーンー
No, don't eat me! I don't taste good!
やめろ！喰わないで！おいら美味くないから！
Num-num...
マンマァー
Help me, bro!
助けて…あにきー！
Huh? Ouch...
ってぇ…
To think I'd meet travelers here.
こんなところに旅の者とは。
What a curiosity you are.
奇特な人もあったものだ
You must not have known,
but it's dangerous here at night.
あなた方は知るまいが、ここは夜は危ない。
A ghoul haunts this place.
あやかしが出るのでな
A ghoul...
あやかし…
Come to my house if you'd like.
よろしければ私の屋敷に来なさらんか？
I wouldn't like to hear of people
being eaten in my mountain village.
わが里の内で人が喰い殺されるのをみすみす眺めても…おれぬのでな
Bro...
あにき…
My name is Sabame.
I am the lord of this land.
私はこの辺りの里を治める、鯖目と申す
I'd like to hear about your travels.
そなたたちの旅の話でも…聞かせてくれ。
Hey, he isn't really a monster, is he?
なぁあにき。あいつ本当にバケモンじゃないんだよな？
I'm not sure.
けど…臭う
Good evening, Lord Sabame.
お晩でがんす、鯖目様
Out on watch?
You are such a hard working man.
夜回りですかい？相変わらずご精が出ますのぅ
I'm just looking out for my village.
なんの。己が里を己が手で守っておるだけのことよ
We live in peace thanks to you, my lord.
鯖目様のおかげで、わしらも安泰ですじゃ
Come to think of it,
where did that monster baby go?
そういえばあいつ、どこ消えちまったんだろう
This is my residence.
ここが私の屋敷だ
Do come in.
さぁさ、遠慮なく通られい
It's an old country dance.
Do you not like it?
田舎芸でしてな。お気に召さぬかな？
More please, lots of it!
おかわり！てんこもりで！
Thanks.
あんがと！
You're a really great guy,
feeding us strangers like this.
おっさん、いいやつだな！
見ず知らずのおいらたちにこんなにごちそうしてくれて
I enjoy listening to travelers' tales.
旅の者の話を聞くのが好きでな。
Since I've never left this land myself.
私はこの地を離れたことがないゆえ
Yeah? But I bet you've got
some interesting stories, too.
そっか。でもここらにも面白そうな話ありそうだぜ？
Like that ghoul in the burnt-out temple.
さっきの焼け跡のあやかしとかさ
It's not a pretty story.
気味のよい話ではないぞ
There used to be a nunnery up there.
あそこにはかつて尼寺があってな
The nun took in orphans
from the surrounding villages.
住職は近隣の里から身寄りのない子供を貰い受けておった
They were forced to work
like farm animals.
まるで牛か馬でも扱うように働かせ
And if they disobeyed...
聞かねばたちまち…
After working for a few years,
they'd be sold off.
そうして何年かすると売り飛ばされてしまうのだ
The heavens must've had enough of it.
天罰が下ったのだろうな。
One night, lightning struck the temple
and set it alight.
ある夜、本堂に稲妻が落ちて火事となり…
It was all gone in a few minutes.
あっという間に焼け落ちてしまった。
Nun, children, and all.
住職も…子供達ももろともに
That's awful. All the kids, too?
そんな…ひでぇじゃねぇかい。子供達までみんな…
We regretted not doing something earlier.
我々も、もう少し早く何とかしてやれなかったのかと…
It's too late for regrets,
but we pray for those poor souls.
今更だが、時折参って冥福を祈っておる
-And the ghoul?
-It's the ghost of the nun.
あやかしは？
住職の成れの果てだ。
She couldn't go up to heaven, I suppose.
成仏できなかったのだろうな…
She appears nightly
and eats those that happen to pass by.
夜な夜な現れては、通りがかったものを喰らうのだ
I'm so glad we weren't one of them.
よかったー！おいらたち喰われなくて。
All thanks to you.
おっさんのおかげだよ
I'm glad to hear that.
それは…何より
It's late now.
さ、今日はもう遅い。
Feel free to stay here and rest
as long as you wish.
遠慮なくこの屋敷に逗留して休まれよ
Hey, bro?
Do you believe everything he said?
なぁ、あにき。さっきの話、どこまでホントだと思う？
About the ghoul, no.
女の霊は違う
Yeah. And about how the temple
was burnt down by lightning.
だよなぁ。それに雷落ちて寺が焼けたってのもさぁ。
Those oil stains must mean
somebody set it on fire.
あの油のシミはどう見ても着け火の跡だ
We'll see in time.
いずれわかる
You think a demon will come here?
来ると思う？鬼神がここに
I-I'm not scared, you know.
こ…怖いわけじゃねーからな？
But jeez, this house sure is cold.
いやー、なんか寒いなぁこの屋敷。
I think there's a draft.
すきま風かなぁ？
Bro, are you asleep?
あにき…寝ちゃった？ちぇ
What you have on your back
can move people and change the world.
お前さん背中のそれは、人を動かし世を変える
It's a source of great power.
でかい力の源になる
Listen now, Dororo.
いいかい、どろろ。
This is your papa's lifelong ambition.
これはお父ちゃんの…命懸けの願いなんだ
What am I supposed to do?
I haven't the slightest clue.
どうしろっていうんだよ…おいらわかんないよ）
Keeping true to your ambition
when it could mean life or death...
食うや食わずの身の上で、それでも志を貫けるのなんて
that isn't something just anyone can do.
ほんの一握りの人間だけだからねぇ
Don't blame me.
I've been on my own all this time.
仕方ねーじゃねーかぃ。オイラずっと1人ぼっちだったんだから
Why'd you have to die, Mama?
どうして死んじゃったんだよ…おっかちゃん
Bro, there's something there!
あ…あにき！なんか来てる！
Bro, wake up! Come on!
あにき！起きて起きて！あ…やばいってば！
-Bro!
-Stand back.
あにき！
退がってろ
It spat silk? Hey!
ねば糸？おい、てめぇ！
You did it, bro!
やったぁ！あにき！
Huh?
な、なに！？
What the...
うわっ、なに！？
What is this?
え？なんだこれ？ゲホッ！ゲホッ
It took the caterpillar.
あ、イモムシを！
Phew, that scared me.
ひぇー、びっくりしたぁ。
It must be some moth or butterfly monster.
あいつきっと、蛾とか蝶のバケモンだな。
This powder makes my skin tingle.
It's not poison, is it?
あにき、この粉なんかピリピリするけど…得じゃないよね
Wash it off.
洗えるか
Let's use that pond in the garden.
庭の池、使っちまうか。
Hey bro? Was that huge thing...?
なぁあにき。あのでかいヤツって、やっぱり…
A demon.
鬼神だ
It took that caterpillar monster away.
あいつ、イモムシのバケモンを連れてったよな。
You think it came to save its kid?
自分の子供を助けに来たってことなのかな
Lord Sabame.
鯖目様
I finally got you some food.
Two of them, too.
久々の餌…それも2つもじゃ。
The children must be happy today.
あの子らも、今日は満足したろ
They could not eat.
喰えませ…なんだ。
It is too strong.
あれは…手強い
You were beaten?
討ち漏らしたというのか
The one The Twelfth could not devour.
12番目の喰い漏らし…
It has come for what was taken from it.
もや、取り戻しに来るとは
I will let nothing and nobody
lay a finger on you or the children.
いかな相手であろうとも、そなたらには指一本触れさせぬ！
For my land and for my people.
この地と…この地に生きるわが民のために
Born into this world
There is no salvation
The distorted shape of the heart
Yet it beats courageously
There is no turning back
Even from the path of evil
Witnessing the withering seasons
We search for the truth
In our ugliness
We don't even recognize the pain
As we peel back the skin
We are forever tormented by our stupidity
But if the dawn never comes
Through the painful night
You who distrusts nothing
You will be able to love
this accursed world
Now that we carry the world
on our shoulders
It's time to take it back
"Maimai-onba"